<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- *************************GO-LICENSE-START******************************
 * Copyright 2014 ThoughtWorks, Inc.
 *
 * Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
 * you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
 * You may obtain a copy of the License at
 *
 *    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 *************************GO-LICENSE-END******************************* -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "cruise_help.dtd">
<chapter title="Running out of disk space">
  <p>After you've had Go running for a while, you may notice the following warning box when browsing Go:</p>
  <img src="resources/images/cruise/admin/out_of_disk_space/1_low_disk_space_on_artifacts.png" />

  <p>If you don't do anything about it, you'll end up seeing the following error:</p>
  <img src="resources/images/cruise/admin/out_of_disk_space/2_out_of_disk_space_on_artifacts.png" />
    
  <p>Go will stop scheduling new pipelines until you make more room, either by compressing large files, attaching a larger hard drive, or by deleting unused artifacts. You could also let Go manage artifact disk space by enabling auto purge of old artifacts.</p>
  
   <section file="delete_artifacts" title="Auto purge old artifacts" collapsed="true"/>


  <section title="Compress large log files" collapsed="true">
    <p>In many cases, the easiest thing to do is compress some of the larger artifacts that you won't frequently have need for. For example, if you have a large log file named 'test.log' and you're running Go server on a unix machine, the following script will gzip those files that haven't been modified in the last 10 days</p>
    <code>find /var/lib/go-server/logs/pipelines -name test.log -mtime +10 -type f -exec gzip -v '{}' \;</code>
    <p>Now, if you add this to a system <exref url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cron">crontab</exref>, your server can compress large artifacts automatically.</p>
  </section>
  <section id="new_mount_for_artifacts" title="Move the artifact repository to a new (larger) drive" collapsed="true">
    <p>If compressing large artifacts is not giving you enough free space, another thing you can do is attach a larger disk drive to store artifacts. After the drive is attached to the system, we can easily change the location Go uses for it's artifact repository.</p>
    <bullets>
      <item>Find the location of the Go configuration file</item>
      <bullets>
        <item>Navigate to the <cref topic="administration_page">Admin</cref> section</item>
        <img src="resources/images/cruise/topnav_admin.png" />
        <item>Click on the "Config XML" tab</item>
        <item>The location of the configuration file is listed here</item>
        <img src="resources/images/cruise/admin/out_of_disk_space/4_find_config_location.png" />
      </bullets>
      <item>Install the new drive</item>
      <item>Shut down Go server</item>
      <item>Copy all files from the original artifact repository location to the new drive</item>
      <item>
          Change the artifact repository location in the configuration file
          <code><![CDATA[
<server artifactsDir="/path/to/new/artifacts">
    ...
</server>]]></code>
      </item>
      <item>Start up Go server and verify you still have access to old artifacts</item>
    </bullets>
  </section>
  <section title="Delete unused artifacts" collapsed="true">
    <p>Another option for making more room is to remove unused (or easily recreatable) artifacts. You may also have old pipelines that you no longer need.</p>
    <p>The directory structure of the artifact repository makes selecting which artifacts are safe to delete easier. The format is:</p>
    <code>[artifacts-dir]/pipelines/[pipelineName]/[pipelineLabel]/[stageName]/[stageCounter]/[jobName]</code>
    <warning>
      <p>Keep in mind that there are two files that Go needs in order to display the <cref topic="job_details_page">Job</cref> or <cref topic="stage_details_page">Stage</cref> Details pages</p>
      <bullets>
        <item>cruise-output/console.log</item>
        <item>cruise-output/log.xml</item>
      </bullets>
    </warning>
  </section>
</chapter>

