<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- *************************GO-LICENSE-START******************************
 * Copyright 2014 ThoughtWorks, Inc.
 *
 * Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
 * you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
 * You may obtain a copy of the License at
 *
 *    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 *************************GO-LICENSE-END******************************* -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "cruise_help.dtd">
<chapter title="Concurrent Modifications to Go's Configuration">
    <p>Go handles concurrent modifications to its configuration. Multiple modifications are merged and saved successfully. Modifications to the same area of configuration would result in a conflict.
    </p> 
    <note>Note: Configuration file is maintained in
        <a href="http://git-scm.com/" target="_blank">git</a>
        version control system. Go leverages git’s merge feature to merge changes from multiple users.
        As expected, concurrent changes to the same section by users would result in a conflict.
    </note>
    <section title="Successful Merge">

        <p>In case of a successful merge, user would see a success message as below:
        </p>
        <img src="resources/images/cruise/admin/successful_config_merge.png"/>
    </section>
    <section title="Merge Conflicts">

        <section title="Handling conflict while using Config XML tab (Go Administrator)">
            <p>In case of a conflict, Go provides an interface with the latest version of config along with the changes made by the user. As an example, if the same job was re-named by two users
                concurrently, the changes from first user would be successfully saved while the second user would see a page similar to the one displayed in the image below.
            </p>
            <p>User needs to re-apply their changes displayed on the left-hand pane, to the editable version on the right and save again.</p>

            <img src="resources/images/cruise/admin/config_xml_merge_conflict.png"/>

        </section>
        <section title="Handling conflict while using Config XML tab (Pipeline group administrator)">
            <img src="resources/images/cruise/admin/group_admin_merge_conflict.png"/>
        </section>
        <section title="Handling conflict while updating configuration via other Admin tabs">
            <p>If two users make similar changes to a pipeline using the ‘Edit Pipeline’ UI, the second user would see the error as displayed below.</p>
            <p>User should backup the required changes from the page. Clicking on ‘RELOAD’ button, would discard user’s changes and reload the page with latest version of the pipeline configuration.
                User should re-apply his/her changes from backup and save again.
            </p>
            <img src="resources/images/cruise/admin/clicky_admin_merge_conflict.png"/>
        </section>
    </section>


</chapter>

