<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- *************************GO-LICENSE-START******************************
 * Copyright 2014 ThoughtWorks, Inc.
 *
 * Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
 * you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
 * You may obtain a copy of the License at
 *
 *    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 *************************GO-LICENSE-END******************************* -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "cruise_help.dtd">
<chapter title="Managing Users">
    <p>Go's user management features allow you to control access to Go and grant role-based permissions.</p>

    <note>All user management features depend on an <cref topic="dev_authentication">authentication mechanism</cref> having been configured in Go. Please ensure you have at least one <cref topic="dev_authentication">authentication mechanism</cref> enabled before attempting to use any of the features mentioned in this chapter.</note>

    <section title="Adding Users">
        <steps>
            <item>Navigate to the Admin section</item>
            <item>Click on the "User Summary" tab</item>
            <item>
                <p>Click the "Add User" button</p>
                <img src="resources/images/cruise/admin/user_summary_add_user.png"/>
            </item>
            <item>Enter a name/email to search for (minimum 2 characters) and click "Search"</item>
            <item>This will perform a search across all authentication mechanisms configured (password file and/or LDAP)</item>
            <item>From the list of results, select the user to add and click "Add User"</item>
        </steps>
        <img src="resources/images/cruise/admin/user_summary_search.png"/>

    </section>

    <section title="Assigning Roles">
        <p>
            Roles allow you to group a set of users with similar functional duties and grant them a common set of permissions.
        </p>
        <p>
            For example, you may have 3 pipelines configured as part of your workflow -- build, acceptance and deploy. You team may consist of 6 developers and 2 testers. With roles, you can group all 6 of your developers into a role called "developers" and your 2 testers into a role called "testers". You'd then assign the following permissions to your pipelines:
        </p>
        <bullets>
            <item>build: Auto triggered pipeline with approval permissions granted to both developers and testers</item>
            <item>acceptance: Auto triggered pipeline with approval permissions granted to testers only</item>
            <item>deploy: Manually triggered pipeline with approval permissions granted to testers only</item>
        </bullets>
        <p>
            With this setup, your entire team has visibility into what each other is doing, but you have controls around which role can do what.
        </p>
        <p>
            <strong>To assign roles to users:</strong>
        </p>
        <steps>
            <item>Navigate to the Admin section</item>
            <item>Click on the "User Summary" tab</item>
            <item>Select the users you want assign roles to, or remove roles from</item>
            <item>Click the "Roles" button to see a list of roles</item>
            <item>Check/un-check the roles you want to assign/remove from the selected users and click "Apply"</item>
            <item>Alternately, you can create a new role to apply to the selected users by typing in the name of a role in the input box and clicking "Add"</item>
        </steps>
        <img src="resources/images/cruise/admin/user_summary_roles.png"/>
    </section>

    <section title="Managing 'Go System Administrator' privilege">
        <p>
            'Go System Administrator' has access to all administrative functions, and has operational access to all parts of a Go installation.
        </p>
        <p>
            User management page allows you to assign admin privileges to or revoke admin privileges from selected users.
        </p>

        <note>This control allows you to modify admin privileges for users(not for roles). Checking 'Go System Administrator' for selected users adds them directly to &lt;admins/&gt; configuration tag. This control is disabled when one or more of the selected users have implicit admin privilege through role(s).</note>
        <p>
            <strong>Assign/Revoke 'Go System Administrator' privilege:</strong>
        </p>
        <steps>
            <item>Navigate to the Admin section</item>
            <item>Click on the "User Summary" tab</item>
            <item>Select the users you want assign/revoke 'Go System Administrator' privilege.</item>
            <item>Click the "Roles" button to load 'Go System Administrator' control</item>
            <item>Check/un-check the 'Go System Administrator' checkbox and click "Apply"</item>
        </steps>
    </section>
</chapter>