<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- *************************GO-LICENSE-START******************************
 * Copyright 2014 ThoughtWorks, Inc.
 *
 * Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
 * you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
 * You may obtain a copy of the License at
 *
 *    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 *************************GO-LICENSE-END******************************* -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "mingle_help.dtd">
<chapter title="Running Go without installation">
    <p>If you want to run Go on a platform which does not have a native installer or want to run Go without requiring to install it, you could do so by using the zip installers.</p>
    <p>Ensure that the <cref topic="system_requirements">system requirements</cref> are met. Specifically:</p>
    <bullets>
        <item>Java Runtime Environment (JRE) version 6 or above</item>
        <item>RAM: 1Gb minimum, 2Gb recommended</item>
        <item>2 GHz (or higher)</item>
    </bullets>
	<section title="Run Go server">
	    <bullets>
	    <item>Download the zip installer for Go server</item>
	    <item>Unzip the installer on a folder of your choice.  It creates a subfolder with the name go-server-&lt;version&gt;</item>
	    <item>Set JAVA_HOME to the installation path of java on the system</item>
	    <item>Open a command prompt and go to the folder</item>
	    <item>If you are on a Windows system, run <strong>start-server.bat</strong></item>
	    <item>If you are on a unix system, run <strong>server.sh</strong>. (Ensure that server.sh is executable)</item>
	    </bullets>
	    <note>If you are on a system which does not support either command, alter the existing scripts suitably and use it</note>

	</section>
	<section title="Run Go agent">
	    <bullets>
	    <item>Download the zip installer for Go agent</item>
	    <item>Unzip the installer on a folder of your choice.  It creates a subfolder with the name go-agent-&lt;version&gt;</item>
	    <item>Set JAVA_HOME to the installation path of java on the system</item>
	    <item>Open a command prompt and go to the folder</item>
	    <item>If you are on a Windows system, run <strong>start-agent.bat</strong></item>
	    <item>If you are on a unix system, run <strong>agent.sh</strong>. (Ensure that agent.sh is executable)</item>
	    <item>Go agent, by default, will attempt to connect to the Go server running on the same system.  If you want it to connect to a different Go server, set the environment variable GO_SERVER or edit the startup scripts suitably</item>
	    </bullets>
	    <note>If you are on a system which does not support either command, alter the existing script suitably and use it</note>

	</section>
</chapter>
