<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- *************************GO-LICENSE-START******************************
 * Copyright 2014 ThoughtWorks, Inc.
 *
 * Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
 * you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
 * You may obtain a copy of the License at
 *
 *    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 *
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 *************************GO-LICENSE-END******************************* -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "cruise_help.dtd">
<chapter title="Go 13.1">
        <section title="New features">
	    <bullets>
                <item id="6669"><strong><cref topic="command_repository">Command Repository</cref></strong>: How do I run maven with Go?  Is it possible to do an EC2 deploy with Go?  What is the syntax if I need to execute a remote command on a linux box?  The answer to these and more are now provided within Go. 
		<p><youtubesingle videoid="fSQZ5hEQbgY"/></p>
		</item>
	    </bullets>
	</section>
	<section title="Enhancements">
	    <bullets>
                <item id="6667"><strong><cref topic="material_update_hung">Notification if material update is hung</cref></strong>: Go server becomes less responsive when some of the processes that it invokes to do material updates stop responding.  Now you get to know when this happens and take suitable steps.
		</item>
                <item id="6497">Support for multiple organizational units (OUs) in <cref topic="dev_authentication" anchor="ldap_authentication">LDAP configuration</cref>.  This allows finer-grained access control.  If your organization has multiple OUs in your corporate LDAP, you can now to choose to specify those OUs, whose users are allowed to use Go.
		</item>
		<item id="6996"><cref topic="Agent_API">Additional agent APIs</cref>: Go now provides an API to list details of all agents and another API to delete disabled agents.</item>
                <item id="6943">Ability to seach community forum from help documentation.  You can now look up community articles from within the help documentation by clicking the Help icon on the center right of each help page.
		</item>
	    </bullets>
	</section>
	<section title="UI changes">
	    <bullets>
	        <item id="6680">Docking of primary header</item>
	        <item id="6725">Docking of breadcrumbs</item>
	    </bullets>
	</section>
	<section title="Bug fixes">
	    <bullets>
                <item id="6896">When a "run on all agents" job involves more than 100 agents, some of the jobs failed reporting completion
		</item>
                <item id="5884">Run-if conditions is shown for Cancel task
		</item>
                <item id="6846">Extraction of <cref topic="pipeline_templates">pipeline templates</cref> not retaining parameters
		</item>
                <item id="6772">Fan-in resolution not happening in some scenarios
		</item>
                <item id="6770">nunit test reports not parsed by Go due to case-sensitivity of file extension
		</item>
                <item id="6893">New pipeline created without using templates shows parameters of the first template, if any
		</item>
                <item id="6674">cctray breakers list returns 'Unknown' as breakers when pipeline has dependency material
		</item>
                <item id="6691">Default column not retained for large search results in add user screen
		</item>
                <item id="6888">In environments page, icon indicating revisions available for deployment is truncated
		</item>
                <item id="6898">Check All functionality not working in Add agents tab in Environments page
		</item>
                <item id="6872">Edit dialogs in Environment tab display incorrect title</item>
		<item id="6621">In pipeline configuration page, when a pipeline is paused/unpaused, the same is not reflected in the screen until refresh
		</item>
		<item id="7060">In certain conditions, sorting of Agents by Free Space throws error when using OpenJDK.
		</item>
	    </bullets>
	</section>
</chapter>
